<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall November 23, 1684 by Gilbert Ironside ...</title>
            <author>Ironside, Gilbert, 1588-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13210794</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13210794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 422:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall November 23, 1684 by Gilbert Ironside ...</title>
                  <author>Ironside, Gilbert, 1588-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield ... for James Good ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING At <hi>White-hall November</hi> 23. 1684.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>GILBERT IRONSIDE,</hi> D. D. VVarden of <hi>Wadham Coll. in Oxon,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED <hi>By His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield</hi> Printer to the Univerſity, for <hi>James Good</hi> Bookſeller near the <hi>Theatre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98505:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING The 23 of <hi>November.</hi> 1684.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Peter cap. 4. ver. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let none of you ſuffer as a Murderer, or as a Thief, or as an Evil-doer, or as a Buſie-body in other mens matters. Yet if any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian let him not be aſhamed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ROM which words we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Prohibition of ſuffering in a bad cauſe: <hi>Let no man ſuffer as a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And tis <hi>a divine Prohibition for the diſcharge of our conſciences upon the pain of ſin. 'Tis the divine favour the Apoſtle aims at, not time ſerving;</hi> He gives this injunction as an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> not as a <hi>States-man,</hi> as an Apoſtle that had the care over all the Chriſtian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98505:3"/>Churches: And if there be any thing extraordinary in that, 'tis the very Apoſtle, that had a ſpecial charge Three times <hi>to feed the Sheep and Lambs of Chriſt. —Let no man</hi> ſays St. <hi>Peter ſuffer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Support and Comfort, and Honour that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the Croſs of Chriſt. <hi>But if any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian let him not be aſhamed.</hi> Of this laſt I ſhall not ſpeak; I hope in this diſtracted, diſputing, luke-warm Age, if yet <hi>Chriſtianity it ſelf</hi> ſhall come to be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, (which God of Heaven forbid) there be not many among us that profeſs the name of Chriſt, will want Blood, nor their Blood Spirit enough to dye for him, who dy'd for them, when he was the Son of God.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs here is to conſider well, what 'tis to <hi>ſuffer as a Chriſtian,</hi> not to be too haſty and poſitive in pronouncing this or that <hi>Rule or Doctrine</hi> to be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. <hi>If any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian, (i.e.)</hi> according to <hi>Chriſt's Inſtitution,</hi> not the fooliſh, no, nor <hi>the wiſe</hi> Fancies of men, Single or in Aſſemblies, a Divine, and Apoſtolieal Chriſtian. We need not, nay we muſt not look for the Image of him any where but as we find it in Chriſt's and his Apoſtles drawing.</p>
            <p>Even the Church it ſelf, when it repreſents Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a right, falls infinitely ſhort of what is in the Bible, as to the Lording it over our Faith, and is not ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98505:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>hardy as to <hi>equal</hi> Her Inſtitutions with Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. And we can never be ſufficiently thankful to God for the Wiſdom with which he inſpir'd the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this Reſpect, <hi>the modeſt, and humble Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (indeed all true Wiſdom is ſuch.) a Wiſdom from above, <hi>Firſt Pure, and then Peaceable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had continued ſo too: But how many Articles of Faith, and how many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Life, have they added to Religion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the belief and practice of them as neceſſary to Salvation, the only cauſe of difference betwixt us?</p>
            <p>We are content with the account of a Chriſtian as we find it in Scripture, and in that we read, they were called Chriſtians firſt at <hi>Antioch,</hi> not at <hi>Rome;</hi> however if any man ſay, <hi>Loe here is Chriſt, or there is Chriſt,</hi> this is a good Chriſtian, that a good Catholick, either in <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> Church, <hi>believe them not,</hi> unleſs you find them ſuch, and only, and meerly ſuch, as he was, when St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>if any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian,</hi> ſuch an one even in his greateſt Sufferings <hi>ought not to be aſhamed:</hi> 'Tis but a thin Expreſſion according to the ſound; but the Figure ſpeaks great things, Let him look upon it as his Honour, and Glory, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The ſpirit of Glory reſteth upon you.</hi> Let him eſteem it as an Excellency, a Preferment, and the ſpecial gift of God, <hi>To you tis
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98505:4"/>given to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt Philip.</hi> 1.29.</p>
            <p>But of this comfortable encouragement I ſhall not ſpeak. My time ſhall be ſpent upon the firſt, The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of ſuffering in a bad cauſe, <hi>Let no man ſuffer as a Murderer, or as a Thief;</hi> thoſe are words eaſy to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and ſo is the next, <hi>an Evil-doer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having mentioned <hi>Thieves and Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> to avoid a further enumeration of the other great Immoralities, concludes them all in one word of <hi>Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers,</hi> and then further adds to ſecure the State, <hi>as a Buſy-body in other mens matters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza</hi> tells us that the <hi>Syriack Verſion</hi> does not read thoſe words, <hi>as a Buſy-body,</hi> and he undertakes to give a reaſon for it, becauſe ſays he, the humor of medling with <hi>other mens matters,</hi> does not ſeem to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe faults that are uſually puniſhed, or are puniſhable, unleſs, <hi>quòd ſoepe in rixas incidunt, qui curioſè ſatagunt aliena, unde poſtea majora mala oriantur. Buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies</hi> naturally fall into controverſies, whence greater Evils may ariſe: and ſurely <hi>that alone,</hi> if there were no other reaſon, is a ſufficient one for the Prohibition in the Text, in an Apoſtle that writ for the peace of Chriſtendome even in private concerns, much more in publick, and State Affairs.</p>
            <p>In the Prohibition it ſelf there are two things to be obſerved. The one ſuppoſed. The other infer'd.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98505:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. Tis ſuppoſed there is a Power for the ſuppreſſing of Vice and Immorality: and not only ſo, but alſo in limiting the ſeveral Ranks and Orders and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, and coercing of them, if as <hi>Buſy-bodies</hi> they tranſgreſs: and the Apoſtle reckons even ſuch Conſtitutions lawful, wholeſome and neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This being the Magiſtrates power, tis manifeſtly the Chriſtian Subjects duty to avoid all the things here mentioned, the <hi>laſt</hi> as well as the <hi>firſt,</hi> and that not only in prudence as to worldly affairs, but upon pain of ſin, and the diſpleaſure of the King of Kings. <hi>Let no man ſuffer not only as a Murderer, and a Thief, and an Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer, but as a Buſy-body in other mens matters, i. e.</hi> 'twould be monſtrouſly ſhameful for Chriſtians to be guilty of either of theſe things, not only of groſs, heathen Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities, but of the later ſort alſo: And there is an Emphaſis in the words <hi>Let none of you Chriſtians:</hi> The Apoſtle here ſuppoſes that all theſe are to ſuffer, and and the Magiſtrate would otherwiſe bear the Sword in vain. I do not love to prove ſuppoſitions, yet when Principles themſelves are diſputed, or miſunderſtood, or neglected, or the Light, and Evidence of them fought againſt, and in a great meaſure quencht, they may well be opened, and the ſtrength of them lay'd before the underſtandings of weak and preſt upon the Conſciences
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98505:5"/>of corrupt men: And of all principles, Obedience to Magiſtrates (the great Eye-ſore) and the Execution of Juſtice, the ſupport of the world will be alwayes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be taught, and preſt upon the conſcience; I ſhall therefore conſider from the words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Power for the ſuppreſſing of Vice, and Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality: Indeed a Toleration of <hi>Vice</hi> was never pleaded for upon Earth: God be thanked, all Immorality ſtands condemned by a Law, what ever the practice of men be, or whatever the Cowardice or Corruption of Judges may be in executing the Laws, or whatever the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Magiſtrates ſometimes may be to ſuſpend the Execution of them in Church or State.</p>
            <p>I know no iniquity eſtabliſhed by a Law, unleſs it be ſome ſort of Theft, and that the very worſt, I mean Sacriledge, and I am very far from being ſure of that, God be thanked for our Laws: The Goſpel hath not all ways, nay ſeldome ſince the Pure and primitive times of it proved ſufficient to <hi>overcome</hi> the baſeneſs of human nature, And no man ever diſputed the Magiſtrates power in making ſuch Laws againſt Immorality.</p>
            <p>There is a great Neceſſity of making of them for two reaſons:</p>
            <p>The firſt is the <hi>Exigence of Mankind,</hi> the ſecond is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of the <hi>Glory of God;</hi> neither of which,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98505:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>without the making of theſe Laws, can be provided for.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, we need not apply our ſelves to fetch Arguments from Divinity, to prove what has been the conſtant voice and experience of the whole world.</p>
            <p>And truly the Glory of God can as little ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making theſe Laws, I mean the Glory of God in this world; for as for his Eternal and Internal, as I may ſo ſay, Glory and Perfection, as likewiſe that which is manifeſted amongſt the Bleſſed Spirits, all our deeds of darkneſs can never caſt any ſhadow upon it, though in this world God's honour is much diſgrac'd by our tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>And one reaſon why it muſt be ſo, is, God hath made the Laws of Nature to be his own in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Indeed they were his own at firſt, by writing them upon our nature, and in our hearts, but he made them his own by a particular Sanction. He did ſo to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> nation, when the Government was purely <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracy,</hi> and God was pleas'd to come down upon the Mount to manage all things himſelf, and to ſpeak the <hi>ten Commandments</hi> to the people. And the Author of our Inſtitution was ſo far from taking that Law away, that he tells us in his firſt Sermon from his mouth, that he <hi>came to fulfill it,</hi> i. e. to fill it up.</p>
            <p>Now if God, as if he was <hi>Pater patrioe</hi> as well as <hi>Pater coeli,</hi> Father of Nations as well as father of Heaven, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98505:6"/>obedience to thoſe Laws which were given us for the ſecurity and peace of the world: tis a ſmall return to his Honour to ſee theſe Laws, His and ours, His as well as ours, His by way of Sanction, becauſe ours by way of benefit, put in execution.</p>
            <p>Nay further, the ſad and ſinful condition of mankind, and the obligation of Evangelical duties, that lie upon us in dealing with men guilty of treſpaſſes, makes it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
            <p>God cannot be honoured without the execution of wrath upon the violation of the Laws of Nature, upon this account God will be honoured in this world, or he will confound it: I ſay, he cannot be honour'd in this world, without this Execution of Wrath. Why ſo? 'Tis plain from the Evil conſtitution of Affairs on the one hand, and the nature of Chriſtianity on the other: The Law of Nature enjoyns us Rules of Juſtice; the Laws of Chriſt enjoyn us, in caſe of wrong, Patience, Meekneſs, and Forgiveneſs, as our particular Province.</p>
            <p>We are forbidden doing any Injury, and we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden all kind of Revenge, when others injure us in our Names, Goods, or Perſons. This was the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Saviour, and this was the Practice of our Saviour: <hi>When he ſuffer'd,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Peter, he committed his cauſe to him that judgeth righteouſly;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives a reaſon for it in the behalf of God, —<hi>Vengeance is mine,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98505:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Rom.</hi> 12.19. Were it not for this Reſervation, <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> and <hi>Tully</hi> had been both in the right, who make it an act of Juſtice to revenge an Injury: an act of Juſtice tis, but ſuch an one as God hath reſerv'd to himſelf, <hi>Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is mine,</hi> and it were inſufferable in us to wreſt his ſword out of his hand.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren were afraid, their Father being dead, he would be avenged on them for Injuries they had done him, <hi>Fear not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for am I in the place of God? Gen.</hi> 50. q. d. <hi>Vengeance belongeth unto Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion therefore is, How doth God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge our Injuries, of which the world is, and will be full?</p>
            <p>Injuries are forbid by the Law of nature, and Injuries will be committed by the corruption of nature, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries muſt be ſuffer'd, and forgiven too by the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Goſpel, and Injuries muſt be revenged too by the Juſtice and Government of the world, but muſt be revenged only by God, —<hi>Vengeance is mine.</hi> But how does God revenge and repay our Injuries? I anſwer, two manner of ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, immediately, by himſelf, and that ſometimes in this world, always in the next.</p>
            <p>Secondly, mediately, by the power deputed unto men, and the Magiſtrates are called <hi>Gods</hi> in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98505:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, by Himſelf, immediately. So <hi>David</hi> comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 26. <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai, Deſtroy him not, for who can ſtretch out his hand againſt the Lord's Anointed, and be innocent? David</hi> ſaid further, <hi>As the Lord liveth, the Lord ſhall ſmite him, or he ſhall come to dye, or he ſhall deſcend into battel and periſh:</hi> and then again adds, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould ſtretch out my hand againſt the Lord's Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this extraordinary vengeance of God the Heathens themſelves had very ſtrong apprehenſions, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted themſelves with expectation of it. So the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Mariners in <hi>Jonah,</hi> when the lot fell upon him, and diſcover'd him. The ſame judgment we find the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> paſs upon St: <hi>Paul,</hi> in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles;</hi> when they ſaw a Viper faſten upon his hands, they conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>No doubt this man was a murderer, whom though he eſcap'd the Sea, yet vengeance ſuffers him not to live.</hi> So <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> when he confeſs'd he ought not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelf of his Superior, comforts himſelf with this Apprehenſion, That the Providence of God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other would do him right. —<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the apprehenſions the Jews and Heathens had of the Juſtice of God, and his divine and immediate vengeance: what we are to have we may learn from our Saviour, ſpeaking of the unrighteous Judge, that for importunities ſake did the widdow right, concludes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98505:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God the righteous Judge, <hi>Shall not he avenge his own Elect, that cry unto him day and night? I tell you,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>he will avenge them ſpeedily, tho he bear long with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is God's firſt way of avenging, but this is in extraordinary and rare caſes, and often, and for the moſt part put off till the great day of Doom, the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of the Lord. And therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a more ordinary and daily way of avenging Injuries, and that is by the hand of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. So we read <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>He is the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon them that do evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what, the vengeance we are forbid to do our ſelves, is it lawful to demand at the hands of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate? Yes, we may, if it be done for one of theſe three ends; Either to correct and amend Offendors, or to terrifie and keep others from offending, or to ſecure Innocent perſons. Theſe ends we find to be Reaſons given in Scripture of puniſhments both in Civil and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts.</p>
            <p>The firſt end is to correct and amend Delinquents. So when <hi>Hymenoeus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> were delivered to Satan, it was, that <hi>they might learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Reaſon of demanding Juſtice, is to terrifie the Inſolent and Proud perſons. So <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. When the Refractory perſon was adjudg'd to be ſlain, 'twas,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98505:8"/>that all the people might <hi>hear and fear, and do no more preſumptuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third end of calling in this vengeance from the Magiſtrate, is the ſecurity of the Innocent. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivers himſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>I wiſh they were cut off that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you.</hi> Theſe are lawful and neceſſary Reaſons, and may and ought to ſway with all good men and true.</p>
            <p>But otherwiſe, for the ſatisfaction of a revengeful humor, as tis uncharitable in us to demand the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, ſo in the Judge or Magiſtrate tis not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to give it. <hi>Nemo ſapiens punit, quia pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed nè peccetur:</hi> 
               <q>A wiſe man never inflicts puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe offences have been committed, but to prevent them for the future that they may not be.</q>
            </p>
            <p>However for the other Reaſons mention'd, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is God's Miniſter, to execute wrath upon them that do evil: And the Apoſtle tells us, he <hi>does not bear the ſword in vain,</hi> i. e. 'twas not given him in vain, and he ought not to bear it in vain.</p>
            <p>So far I ſuppoſe we are all willing to go, if not too willing to revenge all Immoralities againſt our ſelves in goods, names, or perſons; and you will ſay, neither the world, nor God's glory can ſubſiſt without this venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: but we are alſo to conſider, there are alſo Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities againſt the firſt Table. And truly, all men have had ſome ſenſe of many of them, and condemn them;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98505:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and yet generally we uſe our Maker worſe than we uſe our ſelves; we are apt to be moe careleſs of preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's honour, nay the honour of his Being, than of ſecuring our own conveniences, or, it may be, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity of preſerving Peace and Life make proviſion againſt all Immoralities amongſt men in their Perſons, Goods, and Names; and a man ſhall be hang'd for ſtealing what is of little value. As for Spiritual objects, they lie out of ſight, they are ſeen only by Faith, and therefore do not ſo much, ſo powerfully, and ſo conſtantly affect us, God help us in it. But I ſay ſome ſenſe of Religion all men have, and always had.</p>
            <p>The Heathen took care to preſerve the honour of Religion in general, and would by no means endure any that did not own a Deity, or blaſphem'd it, or robb'd it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo far were they from that, that ſometimes they put men to death, though in a miſtake only, as in the cafe of the great and divine <hi>Socrates;</hi> and ſo ſevere were they in this point, that it became capital in <hi>Athens</hi> to accuſe a man of Atheiſm, and not be able to prove it.</p>
            <p>But now 'tis a frightful conſideration, to take a view of the whole world from the beginning in the Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all fooliſh, foul, ſenſleſs Sects of Religion.</p>
            <p>When the Devil could not perſwade men to take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98505:9"/>away all Religion (humane Reaſon was too ſtrong for that) and the knowledge of the Creation of the world by Tradition was too freſh upon the minds of men, (and we hear nothing of Atheiſm before the flood) he perſwaded their eaſy and corrupt underſtandings to bear with different Religions: So the <hi>Children of God</hi> and the <hi>Daughters of men</hi> had a Mungrel Religion before the flood. After the flood the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> had many Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their Empire; the <hi>Perſians</hi> more; the <hi>Groecians</hi> more then they; the <hi>Romans</hi> exceeded all; <hi>Aug. de Civitat. Dei li.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 51. When <hi>Rome</hi> had obtain'd Sovereignty over all Nations, She enthrall'd her ſelf to all their Errors of Religion, <hi>Et magnam ſibi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur aſſumpſſiſſe Religionem, quia nullam reſpuebat falſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem; Leo Mag. Sermone de Petro &amp; Paulo,</hi> entertaining all, She thought She could not miſs of the right: Indeed the <hi>Romans</hi> ſometimes were careful to have no new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion brought in, and did not like the Setters forth of new Gods, but it was for fear of ſome great Alteration to grow thereby amongſt the people, otherwiſe they cared not what Religion men were of, ſo they diſturb'd not the publick peace.</p>
            <p>As for the grounds and reaſons of this Toleration, it is wonderful to behold the Vanity of them: ſome were ſo wickedly fancyful, as to think God was pleas'd with this Variety; So <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the Philoſopher per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98505:9"/>
               <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Socrates</hi> li. 4. c. 32. That <hi>the true God</hi> was delighted with the ſeveral, tho falſe opinions men had of him, thinking, they muſt rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence him the more, being ſo hard to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>Upon what grounds the <hi>Samaritans</hi> went, is not mention'd; But we have the Story in the 2. of <hi>Kings c.</hi> 17. And their Tolleration of Idolatrous Religion ſeems to be only from a ſottiſh Compliance.</p>
            <p>When God ſent Lyons among them, ſays the Text, which ſlew them, and a Prieſt of God taught them <hi>v.</hi> 27. how they ſhould ſerve the Lord. In 33. <hi>v.</hi> the iſſue was, They feared the Lord, and ſerved their own Gods too, after the manner of the Nations; &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 41. <hi>'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, So theſe Nations feared the Lord, and ſerved their Graven Images, both their Children and their Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> And ſo it laſted till our Saviours days, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore told the woman of <hi>Samaria, They Worſhipped they knew not what.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> ſeems to go beyond theſe, tho perhaps out of the ſame Principle, with a great deal of baſe flattery added to it; For <hi>Joſephus</hi> l. 14. <hi>Antiq.</hi> c. 13.14. reports <hi>He built a Temple to</hi> Caeſar <hi>whilſt he repair'd the Temple of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Rhetoria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that he heard of a ſort of Hereticks, <hi>Qui mirabili vanitate omnes Hoereticos lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, &amp; benè ſentire &amp;, vera dicere aſſerebant</hi> (and well he might add, <hi>quòd ita eſt abſurdum, ut mihi incredibile vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur.</hi>)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98505:10"/>Out of Frenſy, or perhaps Atheiſm they prais'd all ſorts of Hereticks,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Ad</hi> Quodvult-Deum, <hi>Hoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis</hi> 72.</note> and juſtified what they ſaid to be true, tho never ſo contrary one to the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Appelles</hi> the Heretick in <hi>Euſebius</hi> had ſomewhat like this Fancy,<note place="margin">Libro <hi>5<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
                  </hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> {fo.} No man was to be queſtioned for his Faith, but that it was ſufficient at any rate to believe in him that was Crucified, excluding only downright Infidels.</p>
            <p>But above all, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate fathom'd the depth of this Wile of Satan, for, <hi>ideò permiſit libertatem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis, quia ſic ſperabat poſſe interire Chriſtianos.</hi> Out of <hi>perfect ſpight</hi> he gave way to a general Toleration, thinking thereby to deſtroy Chriſtianity it ſelf, <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 156.</p>
            <p>This is a true account of the world of old, Heathen, Jewiſh, and Chriſtian, and 'tis a ſad one: As for latter Ages, there have been many pretences to Toleration, of which I need not ſpeak: Only one thing is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of all Ages, namely, <hi>That it has been the Cuſtome</hi> of all <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> to plead for a Toleration them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but never to afford it to the Orthodox Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, witneſs the Jews, the Roman Tyrants, the Arrians, the Donatiſts, (not to ſpeak of the preſent Age) how unmercyful were they?</p>
            <p>Paſs we therefore from the Hiſtory, to our Duty, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98505:10"/>we ſhall be able to gather it out of Scripture, and the Opinion of the Ancient Church, truly Orthodox, and Catholick, abſtracting from the particular Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies now on foot in any part of the Chriſtian world: And I humbly conceive we may certainly conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Toleration in general of any Religion, that is falſe in the ſubſtance of it: For as for <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances</hi> who will inſiſt upon them, <hi>ſo as to make a Schiſm,</hi> but uſe them as he finds them, as <hi>St.</hi> Auſtin <hi>practis'd and advis'd?</hi> But if Religion in the ſubſtance of it be falſe, 'tis an undeniable Maxim, that what we muſt not do our ſelves, we are forbidden to ſuffer in others; we may not allow in others a ſin, which we are forbidden to commit our ſelves; <hi>Non eſt innocens niſi qui cum ſcit prohibere, non poteſt.</hi> He is not to be eſteemed innocent, who knows a thing to be a ſin, unleſs he cannot help it from being committed: And the Canon Law gives a Reaſon,<note place="margin">Decret. parte <hi>13.</hi> distinct. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non caretſcrupulo occultoe Societatis, qui manifeſto crimini deſinit obviare.</hi> A man is to be ſuſpected to have ſome ſecret Society, and combination with that fault he does not hinder.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there cannot but be a great Deformity, and the Beauty of Holineſs is quite loſt by ſuch a Toleration: There is but one God, and Chriſt, and Truth, and Faith, and Church, and tis great confuſion to aſſociate things not ſociable, Light and Darkneſs,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98505:11"/>if it be in our power to hinder it, and there be any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Prudence to hinder it; for there is an abſolute and blind Power, whereby indeed we may do ſuch or ſuch a thing, without any good Reaſon, all circumſtances conſider'd, and without any good effect: And there is a Power of Diſcretion, with which all good and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious things ſhould be accompanied; otherwiſe you may caſt Pearls before Swine, and they may turn and tear you in pieces; And you may pluck up the Wheat with the Tares, <hi>i.e.</hi> You may be the occaſion of doing ſo: For if the Hereticks, which our Saviour means by Tares, prevail in the Confuſion, and get the upper hand, the Church may be deſtroyed. However the Concluſion ſtill ſtands, We are not to tolerate diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Religions, if we can with any Diſcretion, and ſafety prevent it. Otherwiſe a Toleration is not only lawful, but neceſſary: So in the caſe of Ambaſſadors, who have been allways ſuffer'd in the Private uſe of their Religion: One King cannot preſcribe to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Par in parem</hi> &amp;c: So alſo in Reaſons of State, as when Kingdomes be Elective, and obleige themſelves, and cannot without great Confuſion help it, and both Parties are intruſted in the Government.</p>
            <p>So in caſe of Matches; when Kings out of Reaſons of State take Wives out of Kingly Families of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Religion, the abſolute Lawfulneſs of which I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98505:11"/>think can never be queſtioned, but is rather manifeſt from many Inſtances of Scripture, ſuch as <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Rachel,</hi> before the giving of the Law; not to ſpeak of <hi>David</hi> with <hi>Maacha</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the King of <hi>Jeſhuron,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> with <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, after the giving of the Law, which for fear of the ſad effects of Idolatry did forbid ſuch mixtures. I am ſure after the coming of the Goſpel St. <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Believing Party to continue even with the Infidel, who is ſaid, 1 Ep. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> to be bound by the Law ſo to do, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the Law of Marriage,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zam</hi> in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> and the Apoſtle is content for the making of a Marriage Lawful only with one Condition, namely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arabs</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè reſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git ad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum ex fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero.</note> that it be in the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But theſe Exceptions, and the like being provided for, 'tis certainly our Duty to God to ſuppreſs all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Religions, if it be in our Diſcreet Power ſo to do, ſtill obſerving the Apoſtles Rules, which be theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What have we to do to judge thoſe that be without, or thoſe that be not ſubject to the State in which we live? They flatter the Pope, that give him Juriſdiction over all the world.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe that be without, no Chriſtian may draw his Sword againſt Infidels, only for the ſake of Religion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98505:12"/>unleſs there be a ſpecial Warrant from God, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had for the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the <hi>Amalekites:</hi> But if the Unbeliever be a Member of the State in which he lives, he is not to be ſuffer'd in the outward exerciſe of his Religion.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour ſhut up the Temples of Idolaters, and there is the ſame Reaſon againſt the Synagogues of the Jews, and the Moſques of the <hi>Mahometans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As for thoſe that be within the Church by Baptiſm, and Profeſſion, if they fall into Hereſy, or Schiſm, they muſt be corrected and reform'd, but ſtill according to the reſpective offices, Lines, and Powers of men, which are various. The Miniſter muſt do his part; and his office is to ſtand Sentinel, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the firſt Approaches, He muſt try them, which ſay, they are Apoſtles, and are not. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>He muſt blow the Trumpet, and bid the People beware of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> Math. 7. <hi>Beware of the leaven of the Phariſees.</hi> Math. 16. <hi>Beware of Dogs, Beware of Evil-workers, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the Conciſion.</hi> Philip. 3. <hi>He muſt inſtruct in Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> 2 Tim. 2. <hi>He muſt convince the Leaders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them ſharply:</hi> If this prevail not, He muſt uſe the Power of the Keys.</p>
            <p>The Epiſtles of Chriſt to the 7 Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> are altogether to this purpoſe, and that upon condition of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98505:12"/>removing the <hi>Candleſtick</hi> out of its place: in the <hi>2d.</hi> of the <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee,</hi> (to the Church of <hi>Pergamus,) becauſe Thou haſt them that hold the doctrine of</hi> Balaam, <hi>who taught</hi> Baalak <hi>to caſt a ſtumbling-block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of Iſrael, and to commit for nication, and that held the doctrine of the</hi> Nicolaitans, <hi>which thing I hate,</hi> ſaid the Spirit to the Churches. So likewiſe to the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> v. 20. <hi>I have a few things againſt Thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman</hi> Jezebel <hi>to teach and ſeduce my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, no <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition practis'd, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, or the Fathers of the Primitive Church. The <hi>Arrians</hi> indeed went that way.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the people likewiſe muſt do their duty in taking the Alarum from the Miniſter, to <hi>try</hi> the Spirits, upon tryal to have no communication with them in ſacred things, which imports an Approbation of their errors, and an Abrenunciation of the Truth; nor in civil things, if the Church ſo order it.</p>
            <p>Howbeit the people muſt keep within their bounds; The Keys aboliſh not civil Rights, or the Law of Property, much leſs do they diſſolve Allegiance: Suffer they muſt for Truth, not defend or propagate it by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. And in this agree the harmony of Confeſſions in all Reformed Churches, whatſoever ſome turbulent ſpirits of <hi>Scotland</hi> have written to the contrary, and may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98505:13"/>well be uſed by Popiſh writers to cover their own <hi>ſhame</hi> in this kind.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> Power is in the hands of the Magiſtrate, even that of coercion; and, <hi>debet terrenum Regnum coeleſti famulari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt This, even the whole of it, the Papiſts conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declaim, ſaying, That Princes indeed are the chiefeſt rank of men in <hi>Civil Societies,</hi> but not in the <hi>Church;</hi> they muſt have nothing to do here of <hi>themſelves;</hi> it were Sacriledge in them, the Pope muſt do all. We ſay, that Kings and Princes are <hi>cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabuloe,</hi> Guardians of both Tables, <hi>Defenders of the Faith,</hi> not by way of compliment and Title only; and that from their own high Dignity and Calling, not the Pope's Donation; <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Faith,</hi> as well as of <hi>Civil Rights, Epiſcopi ad extra,</hi> to ſee God be religiouſly worſhipp'd; <hi>Nurſing Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> Neither does it follow, that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may act <hi>ad libitum,</hi> or that the people may with a ſafe conſcience acquieſce in any Religion he ſhall be pleas'd to determine, (as Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi>) but tis ſuppos'd he ſhall proceed <hi>juxta verbum,</hi> and therefore to ſtudy the Law of our common Maſter, and to adviſe with Thoſe whoſe Profeſſion it is.</p>
            <p>To this end the Emperors called Synods, and ſet the Bible in the middle. And this practice of old, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things was the commendation of the good King <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98505:13"/>
            <p>In the <hi>2d.</hi> of <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. when the Book of the Law was found, he commanded it to be read before him. <hi>And it came to paſs, when the King heard the words of the Law, that he rent his cloaths.</hi> v. 19. <hi>Becauſe our Fathers have not kept the word of the Lord to do after all that is written in this Book,</hi> i.e. in ſuppreſſing falſe and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Religions. <q>And when the King went up into the houſe of the Lord, and all the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> and Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all the people great and ſmall, (as tis expreſs'd <hi>v.</hi> 30.) and read in their ears all the words of the Book, he not only made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for himſelf, but caus'd all that were preſent in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to ſtand to it, <hi>v.</hi> 32. and took away all the <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations</hi> of other Religions <hi>out of all the countreys</hi> that pertain'd to the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> v. 30.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And this, I ſay, and ſuch like good examples of Kings amongſt the Jews, we find Chriſtian Emperors to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in Eccleſiaſtical ſtory: They ſhut up Heretick Churches, caus'd their books to be burnt, diſabled them to bear Office, to inherit Lands, make Wills, baniſh'd them, and ſometimes put them to death. And this meaſure of Power the Church of <hi>England</hi> requires for her Kings, <hi>Article</hi> 37. the ſame Authority and Power which was in uſe and practice a mongſt the Kings of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for any particular uniform courſe to be taken, the Prince being left to Religious diſcretion, no man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98505:14"/>can be ſo vain to expect it. All is well, if the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection be but proportionable to the corruption, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or leſs, as is ſufficient to preſerve the ſound, and reclaim the ſtraying Party.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and other Fathers, were at firſt much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Coertion, and would have only Perſwaſion us'd; but Experience made them retract, and to juſtifie the lawfulneſs and uſefulneſs and neceſſity of Coertion out of Scripture,<note place="margin">Si enim terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, &amp; non doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba quaſi domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio excide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur.</note> ſo it follow Inſtruction, not go before it, So expreſly, plentifully, and at large, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 48. <hi>Mea primitus ſententia erat neminem ad unitatem Chriſti eſſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, verbo eſſe agendum, diſputatione pugnandum, ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vincendum, ne fictos Catholicos haberemus, quos apertos Hoereticos noveramus. Sed haec opino mea non contradicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium verbis, ſed demonſtrantium ſuperabatur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In another place he tells us, <hi>Nullis bonis in Catholica hoc placet, ſi uſque ad mortem in quenquam licèt hoereticum ſoeviatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Creſcon.</note> and deſires <hi>Donatus</hi> the Proconful of <hi>Africa, Ep.</hi> 127. that he would forget he had <hi>poteſtatem occiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di;</hi> and in his <hi>3d.</hi> Book 50. <hi>chap.</hi> to the aforeſaid <hi>Creſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> he gives another reaſon why he would not have the blood of Hereticks to be ſhed, becauſe all hope is cut off, and it takes away Temporal life, when they are in danger of loſing Eternal: yet in ſome caſes he thinks it fit that Hereticks ſhould dye, as when blaſphemous,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98505:14"/>as the <hi>Manichees,</hi> and abuſing the Sacrament in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; when ſuch beaſts as the <hi>Priſcillianiſts,</hi> when tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous as the <hi>Circumcellians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eodem loco coatra <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conium.</hi> Contra lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras <hi>Betiliani. l. 2.</hi>
               </note> And Laws were made ſpecially after the death of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to that purpoſe, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has brought to the hight of extremity. <hi>Bellarm. de laicis, cap.</hi> 21, 22. But in theſe, and ſuch like caſes as have been mentioned, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, in the opinion of the whole Catholick Church, may, and is to interpoſe. And though Anabaptiſts,<note place="margin">In hoc enim Reges, ſicut iis divinitus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur, Deo ſerviunt in quantùm reges ſunt, ſi in ſuo reguo bona ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant, mala prohibeant, non ſolum quae pertinent ad humanam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatem, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rùm etiam quae ad divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Ep. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra <hi>Creſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi>
               </note> and other Phanaticks, ſay, No Good comes by compulſion, (which is not always true, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> reaſons at large,) yet the practice of Religion contrary to the true is not to be ſuffer'd, but means muſt be us'd, not only to ſecure the Church and the Faith of it, but to reform alſo, if it be poſſible, the Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks themſelves, and to compel them even by mulcts to frequent the Church, intending their Salvation, not Puniſhment: <hi>Imò ſerviunt Reges terrae Chriſto, etiam leges ferendo pro Chriſto:</hi> Ep. 48. <hi>Non odio nocendi, ſed dilectione ſanandi.</hi> Indeed the Underſtanding can be wrought upon by nothing but Perſwaſion, and men can never be ſincere Converts, unleſs the Underſtanding be made to yeild: but alas, in encountring with the <hi>greateſt part</hi> of Secteries, we do not deal much with the underſtanding; many of them are ſuch meerly from an indulg'd cuſtome (when Diſcipline lay aſleep) of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98505:15"/>a ſenſual humour, which lies in itching ears, gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up and down, and always prating, and not knowing what they affirm;<note place="margin">Si doceren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; nonter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerentur, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſtate conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudinis obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati ad capeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendam viam ſalutis pigriùs moverentur. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. priùs citatâ.</hi>
               </note> ſo that a little Reaſon, with a ſteady hand in reſtraining, may quickly be effectual with many that <hi>are let looſe only out of this wanton humour,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Reſtraint Reaſon would ſignifie but little: As for thoſe that be truly obſtinate, though an Angel from Heaven ſhould ſpeak, 'twould be to no purpoſe. But then, though the tongue of an Angel cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade this Beaſt, yet a Sword may ſtop him, and cruſh the foot of the Prophet that rides him; and though no good may be done to him, yet we are bound to hinder him from ſeducing or curſing others.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrates are called <hi>Gods,</hi> as having God's Power to preſerve his Honour and Image, (that indeed is the only reaſon of giving them this Power,) and they that deny them the uſe and application of it, inſtead of <hi>Gods</hi> render them <hi>Idols,</hi> that have feet and walk not, hands and cannot ſtrike. Let no man ſuffer as a <hi>Thief,</hi> or a <hi>Murderer,</hi> or <hi>Evil-doer</hi> in any kind againſt man or God; thoſe that be evil doers in any kind may ſuffer.</p>
            <p>There is one Perſon more in the Text that is to be corrected, and that is a <hi>Buſy-body in other mens matters.</hi> And I hope I am not come into the number by my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſcourſe. A <hi>Buſy-body,</hi> who is that? There is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98505:15"/>no ſuch man in the world, and perhaps now, 'tis ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what an hard matter to give an account of this ſin, and to deſcribe the perſon guilty of it: I am ſure, if it be a hard matter to diſcover it, 'tis much a harder matter to deſtroy it. 'Tis a hard matter indeed, to turn out any one Vice, and 'twill never be done perfectly till the coming of the Son of man; but 'tis impoſſible to rid the world of this ſin, ſo incident to the Activity of mens minds, and ſo pretending to, and ſometimes reſembling the great and eminent Graces of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Knowledge, and Charity, and Zeal the Offspring of it: But in truth, ſo ſuitable to the Pride of nature and life, which not only is in, but domineers in the hearts of moſt men.</p>
            <p>There be ſomethings which at firſt ſight or hearing ſeem to be the plaineſt things in the world, and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves really are ſo, yet by the Corruption of men through weakneſs of mind, ſtrength of Paſſion, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, Perſonal Animoſities, Partiallity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſo perplext, as to become the hardeſt to be underſtood; 'Tis ſo in this of being a <hi>Buſy-body;</hi> We can hardly make men confeſs in private concerns, more hardly in publick Affairs. And yet I do not queſtion, if men would but impartially attend and account themſelves with humble nay honeſt minds, they would quickly find themſelves when guilty; Nay at firſt generally ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98505:16"/>men out of an innate modeſty are not eaſily brought to be guilty of this ſin, and 'tis a kind of a Rape upon them, they are rather by natural Inſtinct kept from it, and in our common converſation no Creature is generally ſo oftenſive in ordinary concerns as the Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical one. However, as much as we have defaced this natural modeſty and baſhfulneſs the great Grace, and Beauty, and Ornament of the mind, there be Rules which will be confeſs'd by all when we ſpeak in general of this ſin to diſcover it by, and they are theſe
<list>
                  <item>1. Inferiors have no right to meddle with Superiors at all, unleſs it be to defend, and obey: nothing elſe, not ſo much as to councel unleſs call'd to it: much leſs to reprove ſaucily, or contumeliouſly to expoſe. Nor</item>
                  <item>2. Authority over their Equalls. Nor any men</item>
                  <item>3. Any thing to do out of their calling.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All this is plain by Reaſon, more manifeſt by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and enforc'd upon us; <hi>By what Authority doſt thou theſe thing?</hi> ſaid the Jews to Chriſt, who own'd the reaſonableneſs of the Queſtion; and at an other time, when one came to him to engage him about the dividing of an Inheritance, our Saviour turn'd him away with a ſhort and ſharp Anſwer. <hi>Man who made me a Judge over you?</hi> Neither would he enter upon his own office till
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98505:16"/>the time appointed of his Father. <hi>My hour is not yet come:</hi> And at an other time, he checks the forwardneſs and curioſity of St. <hi>Peter</hi> for only enquiring after the Fate of St. <hi>John. If I will that he tarry till I come, what's that to thee? follow thou me, prepare for thy own buſineſs:</hi> And St. <hi>Paul: What have I to do to Judge thoſe that be without?</hi> And as for thoſe that be within, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Though,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>I ſhould boaſt of my Authority,</hi> which as an Apoſtle was univerſal over all the world, <hi>I ſhould not be aſhamed,</hi> yet how often does he there ſpeak of <hi>lines</hi> and <hi>meaſures</hi> diſtributed to others, and agreed upon, and keeping himſelf from theirs, and within his <hi>own</hi> line?</p>
            <p>Nay further, (to obviate the ranting objection which the rage of Enthuſiaſm has prompted ſome to make, and the Concluſions and Blaſphemies, of which we have ſeen and felt) when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſlew the Egyptian, St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> thinks it was a zeal, not according to knowledge; Thoſe that are not of his mind (as I think moſt are not) ſay 'twas by a ſpecial Commiſſion from God,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> and was the Firſt Inſtance of his being appointed Leader of his People: And indeed, after <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, we have the like inſtances in <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>extraordinary</hi> caſes: So we read <hi>the Spirit of the Lord</hi> came upon <hi>Gideon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maimon. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Nevochim p. 316.</note> 1 <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.34. <hi>i.e.</hi> according to the general Interpretation of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, By a Prophetical rapture he was inſpir'd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98505:17"/>to do thoſe Heroick Acts that are recorded of him in he 7th <hi>chap.</hi> without the help of meanes. And ſo it was indeed with all the Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as is expreſly ſaid <hi>chap.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 3. When the Lord raiſ'd them up Judges, <hi>i. e.</hi> in their Confuſions appointed them extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, 'tis ſaid the <hi>Lord was with the Judge,</hi> extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſtill, to deliver them out of the hand of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. So in the 11 <hi>chap.</hi> 29. <hi>ver.</hi> 'tis ſaid <hi>the Spirit of the Lord came upon Jeptha,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 33. we have his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits: and in the 14, and 19. <hi>verſes</hi> we have the ſame words of <hi>Sampſon. The ſpirit of the Lord came upon</hi> Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The like of <hi>David</hi> in encountring the Lyon and the Bear, and <hi>Goliah</hi> with a Sling. But what is this to the madneſs of our people? If our Zealots pretend to the ſame extraordinary calling, and the ſame Spirit, let them ſhew their Faith by their Works, let them do as <hi>Moſes</hi> did with <hi>Pharaob,</hi> and at the Red Sea; nay, let them do as <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>Jeptha,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and <hi>David, i. e.</hi> let them <hi>work miracles,</hi> bring to paſs Heroick Acts without proper and competent means.</p>
            <p>The Sum is, and it ought to be the <hi>governing</hi> Rule in our <hi>whole lives,</hi> We are to do our Duties when called to it, not elſe, no not in the Acts of our general calling as we are Chriſtians. Let not this ſeem ſtrange to any. The great Duty of Chriſtianity, is to believe with our <hi>hearts,</hi> and confeſs with our <hi>mouths,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus is the</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98505:17"/>Chriſt: neither is it ſufficient to keep Faith only in our hearts, as ſome Hereticks in the Primitive times blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, though it be to <hi>ſave our lives,</hi> but then 'tis when we are <hi>requir'd</hi> to make Confeſſion with our mouths; and the Ancient Church, to check the Forwardneſs and blind zeal of ſome haſty Chriſtians, refus'd thoſe that <hi>offer'd</hi> themſelves to the rage of Perſecution, forbid'em I ſay to be taken into the Catalogue of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe for our Duties to men, we are in 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> requir'd to do <hi>good to all men,</hi> but tis, as is there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, <hi>as we have opportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for particular Callings, we have the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Rules in two Epiſtles: In the 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>All members</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>have not the ſame office,</hi> and therefore <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>let every one attend on the office wherein he is plac'd,</hi> whether it be Miniſtry. Teaching, or Ruling. <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. The ſame counſel we have 1 <hi>Ep. Cor.</hi> 7.20. <hi>Let every man abide in the ſame Calling wherein he was called; Art thou call'd being a Servant, care not for it:</hi> v. 21. <hi>though if thou mayſt be made free, uſe it rather.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 24. he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it again, and to enforce it upon them, uſes the great engaging term of Chriſtianity, <hi>Brethren, let every man in the Calling wherein he is called abide with God;</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe you ſin againſt the common notion of <hi>Brethren,</hi> you walk not as Chriſtians, and therefore <hi>2ly.</hi> you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the great bleſſing that attends our living ſuitably
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98505:18"/>to that Relation, neither do you <hi>abide with God,</hi> and how then can you expect God's favour when you go away from him? God's Protection to his Church is promis'd upon this condition. In the 90 <hi>Pſalm</hi> it is written, <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee,</hi> and if they have charge over us, we need not doubt the ſervices of other creatures, but then, tis <hi>in all thy ways,</hi> not elſe, and That clauſe, the Lyer and the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer from the beginning left out in his Temptation to our Lord.</p>
            <p>Tis very obſervable, how particular the Apoſtles are in laying out the reſpective Duties of Inferiours, (<hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> in <hi>this</hi> world is the <hi>great</hi> thing,) the ſins of <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors</hi> are remitted to the <hi>other</hi> world, and then <hi>Great men ſhall be greatly tormented.</hi> But the Apoſtles are in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more exact in their commands upon Chriſtendom, than in laying out the Duties of Servants to Maſters, (not ſo much as <hi>anſwering again.</hi>) Children to Parents, Wives to Husbands, all Inferiors to their Betters, valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of men by the diſcharge of theſe offices. And twas good advice therefore of a Cardinal,<note place="margin">Jackſon <hi>Tone</hi> 1. p. 232.</note> (much commended by a great Divine of our Church,) in reading of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, to begin with the end of them, which contain the plain Duties of a Chriſtian life, private and publick, for being once well acquainted with them, we ſhall more eaſily attain to the true ſenſe of the former part, which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98505:18"/>being uſually Doctrinal are the more difficult.</p>
            <p>And as the Apoſtles were thus careful in enjoyning the Duties of theſe particular Callings, ſo the Chriſtians were as careful in performing them, though <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>baſe</hi> ones.</p>
            <p>When the Publicans and Souldiers chang'd their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, they kept their Callings ſtill, would fight for their Emperor, and dye for Chriſt at the ſame time; not but that Callings may and muſt be ſometimes changed too, as if one be ſubordinate to the other, or in caſe of diſability of Body, Mind, Eſtate, or Private ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as when <hi>Paul</hi> made Tents, and we have power over our ſelves, and be at our own diſpoſal; —<hi>If thou mayſt be made free, uſe it rather,</hi> never out of Pride, Lightneſs, Ambition, Covetouſneſs, Idleneſs, Pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticalneſs, and as Buſy bodies, and without Authority. For what I pray makes a Calling, either to a Profeſſion or ſingle Action, but (firſt) Fitneſs of Abilities, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Authority? both of them neceſſary always, but the latter abſolutely, and in the higheſt degree. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when men loath the Stations in which God hath ſet them, and either utterly abandon them, or reach at thoſe Imployments which in the ordinary courſe of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence are deny'd them, when he ſhall teach that ought to learn, and he command that ought to obey, ſuch Inverſions and tranſpoſing of things are no more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98505:19"/>hurtful to men, then hateful to God.</p>
            <p>So much for Profeſſions and Callings without Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. The like muſt be ſaid concerning ſingle Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, upon any emergent occaſion. When <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-Smith, in the 19. <hi>Acts,</hi> being afraid, upon the account of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s preaching, of loſing his Trade in making Shrines for the Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> of his own head had called the Craftsmen together, though he ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably in the behalf of the great Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> whom all <hi>Aſia</hi> and the world worſhipp'd, and had fill'd his hearers with wrath againſt St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the whole City with confuſion, crying out for the ſpace of two hours, <hi>Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Epheſians, and yet the biggeſt part knew not for what they came together, the Town-clerk, to ſtill the people, very wiſely and very loyally told them, <q>If <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his Crafts-men have a matter againſt any man, the Law is open, and there are Deputies, or, (as tis in the Margent of our Bible) the Court-days are kept, let them plead one another, and it ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd in a lawful Aſſembly, and ye ought to be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and do nothing raſhly, for we are in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accus'd for this days riot, for as much as there can be no cauſe given for this concourſe of people.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Church, examine the whole Bible, Old and New Teſtament, you will find Prieſts, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, and all the People of God, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98505:19"/>the Son of God himſelf ſubmitting and ruling their outward behaviour by humane Conſtitutions and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as carefully as this Town-clerck. The <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> and the life and death of Chriſt are perfect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Emperial Laws. The Apoſtles refer themſelves to them, Firſt, for Obedience, and then for Protection. We have them both notably at once in St. <hi>Paul. I appeal to</hi> Caeſar. <hi>and I am a Roman;</hi> and when wrongfully impriſon'd in the 16 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the Inferiour Magiſtrates fear'd, when they heard they were Romans, and ſent to ſet them at Liberty privily, no, ſays St. <hi>Paul, They have beaten us openly uncondem'd, being Romans, and have caſt us into Priſon, and now would they thruſt us out privily? Nay verily, let them come them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and fetch us out.</hi> v. 37. But their Obedience to the Laws they allways perform'd ſincerely and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; and upon much better Principles then any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under Heaven among whom they liv'd; other men did it for fear of wrath, Chriſtians for Conſcience ſake. <hi>You muſt needs be ſubject for Conſcinenc ſake, Rom.</hi> 13.5. We are in danger of being call'd on queſtion for this days Riot, ſaid the Town-clerck of <hi>Epheſus, we ſin againſt God</hi> would the Chriſtians have ſaid.</p>
            <p>Indeed if things were purſu'd home to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and thence to their diſmal Conſequences, men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98505:20"/>may learn their Obligations to humane Laws, as well as to the Laws of nature, even by the light of nature: The <hi>Thief,</hi> the <hi>Murderer,</hi> and the <hi>Evil-doer</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by the Laws of nature, the <hi>Buſy-body</hi> by the Laws of the State, which hath power by the Law of nature to make Laws ſufficient to preſerve it ſelf; and is the firſt Dictate of the Law of Nature concerning men combin'd in Societies; and tho in themſelves ſome ſins againſt the other immediate Laws of Nature, and theſe againſt the State are not <hi>comparable,</hi> yet as to the Peace, Tranquility, and Comfort of the world, the ſins which ariſe from this <hi>Pragmatical</hi> Principle, are much the worſe, and generally the cauſes of the others alſo. And who doubts but the Debauchery of the laſt Age was the effect of the War, and that War caus'd by this very Principle? 'Tis therefore a <hi>true and a wiſe ſaying, Sedition is worſe then Murder,</hi> and 'tis pity the ſaying is found ſo often in the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and ſo ſeldome to be met with in the <hi>Practice</hi> of Chriſtians, I ſay, If things were rightly purſu'd to their Origine and Conſequences, this Sin is manifeſtly diſcover'd by the Light of Nature, but no Condemnation of it comparable to what we find in the Chriſtian Religion; That's a Religion, which in its very Conſtitution aimes at the peace and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mankind, a Religion which is exercis'd in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and Self-denyal, in Thanks-giving for other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98505:20"/>mens Parts, Gifts, Powers, Preferments, and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and above all in a perfect Submiſſion to the holy will of God in his wiſe governing of the world.</p>
            <p>The Concluſion therefore muſt be that of <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.10. <hi>My Son meddle not with many matters,</hi> and the Councel is there back'd with Three notable Reaſons, <hi>For if thou meddle, thou ſhalt not be innocent,</hi> (<hi>there is ſin the caſe</hi>) <hi>and if thou follow after, thou ſhalt not obtain,</hi> (<hi>Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is threatned</hi>) <hi>neither ſhalt thou eſcape by flying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be Three things in the New Teſtament which are threatned with ſignal judgments in this life:</p>
            <p>The Firſt is <hi>doing evil that good may come of it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Grotium</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe damnation</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>is juſt. Rom.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>The Second is <hi>Profaning the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. They that eat unworthily eat damnation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>The Third is <hi>Profaning of the ſupreme Powers. They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation. i. e.</hi> Theſe Three ſins make men liable not only to the divine wrath hereafter, (for ſo all ſins without Repentance expoſe to Damnation) but uſually they are alſo attended with ſignal judgments in this life. <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation, and they that meddle
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98505:21"/>with many matters ſhall not eſcape, no not by flying,</hi> a Curſe ſhall follow and overtake thee; And ſo let it upon all the Troublers of the Earth, that our Kings may be at Reſt, and we may lead a quiet life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icunque vos ex occaſione legis imperialis, non dilections ſed inimicandi odio perſequitur, diſplicet nobis; &amp; quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis res veſtras falſo appellatis, quas nec juſti poſſidetis, &amp; ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum leges Regum terrenorum amittere juſſieſtis, quiſquis tamen ex occaſione hujus legis quam Regesterrae Chriſto Servientes ad emendandam vestram impietatem promulgaverunt, res proprias veſtr as cupidè appetit, displicet nobis. <hi>Aug. Ep. 48.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
